In this and the next video,
在这节和下节视频中
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
I'd like to tell you about one
我想给你介绍
possible extension to the
我们目前为止学习的异常检测算法的
anomaly detection algorithm that we've developed so far.
一种可能的延伸
This extension uses something called the multivariate
这个延伸使用到多元高斯分布 (multivariate Gaussian distribution)
Gaussian distribution, and it
has some advantages, and some
它有一些优势
disadvantages, and it can
也有一些劣势
sometimes catch some anomalies that the earlier algorithm didn't.
它能捕捉到一些之前的算法检测不出来的异常
To motivate this, let's start with an example.
为了理解这个算法 我们先来看看一个例子
Let's say that so our unlabeled data looks like what I have plotted here.
假设我们的没有标签的数据看起来像这张图一样
And I'm going to use
我要使用数据中心的监控机的例子
the example of monitoring machines
in the data center, monitoring computers in the data center.
就是在数据中心监控计算机的例子
So my two features are x1
所以我的两个特征变量
which is the CPU load and x2
x1 是 CPU 的负载和
which is maybe the memory use.
x2 可能是内存使用量
So if I take
所以如果我
my two features, x1 and x2,
把这两个特征变量 x1 和 x2
and I model them as Gaussians then
当做高斯分布来建模
here's a plot of
这个是特征变量
my X1 features, here's a
x1 绘制的图
plot of my X2 features,
这个是特征变量 x2 的图
and so if I fit a
如果我能找到一个
Gaussian to that, maybe I'll
它所符合的高斯分布
get a Gaussian like this, so
我得到的高斯分布可能是这样的
here's P of X 1,
所以这是 p(x1;
which depends
它的参数 μ1
on the parameters mu 1, and
sigma squared 1,
和 σ1 的平方 )
and here's my memory used, and,
然后这是内存使用量
you know, maybe I'll get a Gaussian
可能我会得到这样的一个高斯分布
that looks like this, and this is my P of X 2,
这是 p(x2;
which depends on mu 2 and sigma squared 2.
参数 μ2 和 σ2 的平方 )
And so this is
这就是
how the anomaly detection algorithm
异常检测算法给 x1 和 x2 建模的方法
models X1 and X2.
Now let's say that in the
现在假如说
test sets I have an
在测试集中
example that looks like this.
有一个这样的样本
The location of that green
在这个绿色叉的位置
cross, so the value of
它的 x1 的值是 0.4 左右
X 1 is about 0.4, and the value of X 2 is about 1.5.
x2 的值是 1.5 左右
Now, if you look at
现在 如果你看这些数据
the data, it looks like,
看起来它们大部分
yeah, most of the data data
lies in this region, and
都在这个范围内
so that green cross
所以这个绿色叉
is pretty far away from any of the data I've seen.
离这里看到的任何数据都很远
It looks like that should be raised
看起来它应该被当做
as an anomaly. So, in my
一个异常数据
data, in my, in the
所以我的
data of my good examples,
好的样本的数据
it looks like, you know, the
看起来
CPU load, and the
CPU 负载和内存使用量
memory use, they sort
of grow linearly with each other.
是彼此线性增长的关系
So if I have a
所以 如果我有一台机器
machine using lots of CPU,
CPU 使用量很高
you know memory use
那么你就知道
will also be high, whereas this
内存使用量也会很高
example, this green example it looks like
但是这个绿色样本
here, the CPU load is
看起来 CPU 负载很低
very low, but the memory use
但是内存使用量很高
is very high, and I just
我以前从没在训练集中见过这样的
have not seen that before in my training set.
It looks like that should be an anomaly.
看起来它应该是异常的
But let's see what the anomaly detection algorithm will do.
但是我们来看一下异常检测算法会怎么做
Well, for the CPU load, it
对于 CPU 负载
puts it at around there
这个绿色叉差不多在 0.5 这里
0.5 and this reasonably high
有相当高的可能性
probability is not that
它离看到的其它样本不远
far from other examples we've seen,
maybe, whereas, for the
相对的 对于内存使用量
memory use, this appointment, 0.5,
这个点是 0.5
whereas for the memory
而对于内存使用量
use, it's about 1.5, which is there. Again,
它是差不多 1.5 在那里
you know, it's all to
它在这个高斯分布的尾部
us, it's not terribly Gaussian, but
the value here and the value
但是这里的值和这里的值
here is not that different
与看到的其他那些样本
from many other examples we've
没有太大差别
seen, and so P of
所以 p(x1) 会很高
X 1, will be pretty high,
reasonably high.
会比较高
P of X 2 reasonably high.
p(x2) 也会比较高
I mean, if you look at this
我的意思是 如果你看这幅图
plot right, this point here,
这里这个点
it doesn't look that bad, and
看起来它并没那么差
if you look at this plot, you
然后如果你看这幅图
know across here, doesn't look that bad.
这个叉 看起来也不那么差
I mean, I have had examples with
我的意思是 有的样本
even greater memory used, or
内存使用量更高
with even less CPU use,
或者 CPU 使用量更低
and so this example doesn't look that anomalous.
所以这个点看起来不是很异常
And so, an anomaly detection algorithm
所以 一个异常检测算法
will fail to flag this point as an anomaly.
不会将这个点标记为异常
And it turns out what
可以看出来
our anomaly detection algorithm is
我们的异常检测算法
doing is that it is
不能察觉到
not realizing that this blue
ellipse shows the high
这个蓝色椭圆所表示的好样本概率高的范围
probability region, is that, one
of the thing is that, examples here,
它所做的是
a high probability, and the
这部分样本是高概率的
examples, the next circle
外面一些的圈里面的样本
of from a lower probably, and
是好样本的概率低一些
examples here are even
而这里的样本概率更低
lower probability, and somehow, here
然后事情就变成了
are things that are, green cross
那里的绿色叉
there, it's pretty high probability,
是好样本的概率挺高
and in particular, it tends to think
具体来说
that, you know, everything in this
它倾向于认为所有在这区域中的
region, everything on the
在我画的这个圈上的样本
line that I'm circling over, has, you know, about equal probability,
都具有相同的概率
and it doesn't realize that something
它并不能意识到
out here actually has
这边的其实比那边的
much lower probability than something over there.
概率要低得多
So, in order to fix
所以 为了解决这个问题
this, we can, we're going to
我们要开发一种
develop a modified version of
改良版的异常检测算法
the anomaly detection algorithm, using
something called the multivariate
要用到一种
Gaussian distribution also called the multivariate normal distribution.
叫做多元高斯分布或者多元正态分布的东西
So here's what we're going to
所以这是我们要做的
do. We have features x
我们有特征变量 x
which are in Rn and
它属于 Rn
instead of P of X 1, P of X 2, separately,
我们不要把 p(x1) p(x2) 分开
we're going to model P of
而要建立一个 p(x) 整体的模型
X, all in one go,
so model P of X, you know, all at the same time.
就是一次性建立 p(x) 的模型
So the parameters of the
多元高斯分布的参数是向量 μ
multivariate Gaussian distribution are mu,
which is a vector, and sigma,
和一个 n 乘 n 矩阵 Σ
which is an n by n matrix, called a covariance matrix,
Σ 被称为协方差矩阵
and this is similar to the
它类似于我们之前
covariance matrix that we
在学习 PCA
saw when we were working
也就是主成分分析的时候
with the PCA, with the
principal components analysis algorithm.
所见到的协方差矩阵
For the second complete is, let
我们来试着完成这个
me just write out the formula
让我来写出
for the multivariate Gaussian distribution.
多元高斯分布的公式
So we say that probability of
我们说 x 的概率
X, and this is parameterized
确定它的参数是
by my parameters mu and
我的参数 μ 和 Σ
sigma that the
probability of x is equal
x 的概率等于
to once again
再说一次
there's absolutely no need to memorize this formula.
完全没有必要去记这个公式
You know, you can look it up
因为你可以在
whenever you need to use
任何需要用它的时候找到它
it, but this is what
但是 x 的概率
the probability of X looks like.
看起来是这样的
Transverse, 2nd inverse, X
转置 Σ 的逆
minus mu.
x-μ
And this thing here,
这边这个东西
the absolute value of sigma, this
Σ 的绝对值
thing here when you write
当我们写这个符号的时候
this symbol, this is called
这个东西叫做 Σ 的行列式 (determinant)
the determent of sigma
and this is a mathematical function
它是一个矩阵的数学函数
of a matrix and you really
你不需要知道
don't need to know what the
determinant of a matrix is,
矩阵的行列式是什么
but really all you need to
你真的需要知道的
know is that you can
就是可以在 octave 里
compute it in octave by using
使用 octave 命令
the octave command DET of
det(Sigma) 来计算它
sigma.
Okay, and again, just be clear, alright?
好 再确认一次
In this expression, these sigmas
在这个表达式中
here, these are just n by n matrix.
这些 Σ 是 n 乘 n 矩阵
This is not a summation and
这不是一个和号
you know, the sigma there is an n by n matrix.
这个 Σ 是一个 n 乘 n 矩阵
So that's the formula for P
所以那就是 p(x) 的公式
of X, but it's
但是更有趣
more interestingly, or more importantly,
或者说更重要的是
what does P of X actually looks like?
p(x) 到底什么样子
Lets look at some examples of
我们来看一些
multivariate Gaussian distributions.
多元高斯分布的例子
So let's take a
我们来看一个二维的例子
two dimensional example, say if
I have N equals 2, I
如果我有 n 等于 2
have two features, X 1 and X 2.
两个特征变量 x1 和 x2
Lets say I set MU to
如果说我让 μ 等于 0
be equal to 0 and sigma
to be equal to this matrix here.
让 Σ 等于这个矩阵
With 1s on the diagonals and 0s on the off-diagonals,
让对角线上的值等于 1 非对角线上的值等于 0
this matrix is sometimes also called the identity matrix.
这个矩阵有时会被叫做单位矩阵 (identity matrix)
In that case, p of
在这个情况下
x will look like
p(x) 看起来会是这样
this, and what
我在这个图里展示的是
I'm showing in this figure is, you know,
for a specific value of X1
对于一个特定的 x1 的值
and for a specific value of
和一个特定的 x2 的值
X2, the height of
这个面的高度
this surface the value
of p of x. And
就是 p(x) 的值
so with this setting the parameters
所以在这个参数设定下
p of x is highest when
p(x) 在 x1 和 x2 都等于 0 时最高
X1 and X2 equal zero 0,
so that's the peak of this Gaussian distribution,
那就是高斯分布的峰值
and the probability falls off with this
然后这个概率
sort of two dimensional Gaussian or
这个二元高斯分布
this bell shaped two dimensional bell-shaped surface.
随着这个二维钟形的面衰减
Down below is the same
下面这个图和上面是一样的
thing but plotted using a
但它是用等高线
contour plot instead, or using different colors,
或者说不同颜色画的图
and so this
所以中间这里这个
heavy intense red in the
很强烈的暗红色
middle, corresponds to the highest values,
对应的是最高值
and then the values decrease
然后这个值降低
with the yellow being slightly lower
黄色表示低一点儿的值
values the cyan being
青色表示更低一些的值
lower values and this deep
这里的深蓝色
blue being the lowest
表示的是最低的值
values so this is really the same figure but plotted
所以这个其实是同一张图
viewed from the top instead, using colors instead.
就是才用俯视的角度 并且使用了颜色
And so, with this distribution,
所以 从这个分布
you see that it faces most
你可以看出来
of the probability near 0,0
大部分概率都在 0 0 附近
and then as you go out
然后 随着从 0 0 这个点往外延伸
from 0,0 the probability of X1 and X2 goes down.
x1 和 x2 的概率下降
Now lets try varying some
现在我们来试试
of the parameters and see
改变一些参数
what happens. So let's
然后看看会发生什么
take sigma and change it
我们来改变一下 Σ
so let's say sigma shrinks a
假如说缩小一下 Σ
little bit. Sigma is a
Σ 是一个协方差矩阵
covariance matrix and so it
所以它衡量的是方差
measures the variance or the
variability of the features X1 X2.
或者说特征变量 x1 和 x2 的变化量
So if the shrink
所以如果缩小 Σ
sigma then what you get
那么你的得到的是
is what you get is that the
width of this bump diminishes
这个鼓包的宽度会减小
and the height also
高度会增加一点
increases a bit, because the
因为在这个面以下的
area under the surface is equal to 1.
区域等于 1
So the integral of the
所以这个面以下的
volume under the surface is
体积的积分等于 1
equal to 1, because probability
因为概率分布的积分
distribution must integrate to one.
必须等于一
But, if you shrink the variance,
但是 如果你缩小方差
it's kinda like shrinking
相当于缩小 Σ 的平方
sigma squared,
you end up with a narrower distribution, and one that's a little bit taller.
你会得到一个窄一些 高一些的分布
And so you see here also the
在这儿你也看到
concentric ellipsis has shrunk a little bit.
这些同心椭圆也缩小了一些
Whereas in contrast if you were to increase sigma
而相对的 如果你
to 2 2 on the
增加 Σ 对角线上的值到 2 2
diagonals, so it is now two
所以它现在是单位矩阵的二倍
times the identity then you end up with a
那么最后你会得到
much wider and much flatter Gaussian.
一个更宽更扁的高斯分布
And so the width of this is much wider.
所以这个的宽度会更宽
This is hard to see but this
虽然很难看出来
is still a bell shaped bump,
但这还是一个钟形的鼓包
it's just flattened down a lot,
它只是扁平了很多
it has become much wider and
它变得更宽了
so the variance or the
所以 x1 和 x2 的方差或者变化量变大了
variability of X1 and X2 just becomes wider.
Here are a few more examples.
下面再举几个例子
Now lets try varying
现在我们试一下
one of the elements of sigma at the time.
一次改变 Σ 的一个元素
Let's say I send sigma to
假如说我把 Σ
0.6 there, and 1 over there.
改为这里是 0.6 那里是 1
What this does, is this
它所做事情的是
reduces the variance of
减小第一个特征变量 x1 的方差
the first feature, X 1, while
keeping the variance of the
同时保持第二个特征变量
second feature X 2, the same.
x2 的方差不变
And so with this setting of parameters, you can model things like that.
在这个参数设置下 就可以给这样的东西建模
X 1 has smaller variance, and
x1 有小一些的方差
X 2 has larger variance.
而 x2 有大一些的方差
Whereas if I do this,
然而如果我这样做
if I set this
把这个矩阵设置为 2 1
matrix to 2, 1
then you can also model
那么你也可以
examples where you know here
建立这样的模型
we'll say X1 can have take
x1 的变化范围比较大
on a large range of values
whereas X2 takes on a relatively narrower range of values.
而 x2 的变化范围则窄一些
And that's reflected in this
它也被反映到这张图上了
figure as well, you know where,
the distribution falls off
这个分布随着 x1 远离 0
more slowly as X 1
moves away from 0,
下降得更缓慢
and falls off very
而随着 x2 远离 0
rapidly as X 2 moves away from 0.
下降得非常快
And similarly if
类似地
we were to modify
如果我们改变
this element of the
矩阵的这个元素
matrix instead, then similar to the previous
那么会类似于上一页
slide, except that here where
除了在这儿
you know playing around here saying
我们说 x2 的变化区间非常小
that X2 can take on
a very small range of values
我们说 x2 的变化区间非常小
and so here if this
所以在这里 如果这个是 0.6
is 0.6, we notice now X2
我们发现现在 x2 的变化区间
tends to take on a much
smaller range of values than the original example,
比原来的例子要小很多
whereas if we were to
然而如果我要让 Σ 等于 2
set sigma to be equal to 2 then
that's like saying X2 you know, has a much larger range of values.
这就是说让 x2 有大一些的变化区间
Now, one of the cool
现在 多元高斯分布的
things about the multivariate
Gaussian distribution is that
一个很棒的事情是
you can also use it to
你可以用它给数据的
model correlations between the data.
相关性建立模型
That is we can use it to
我们可以用它
model the fact that
来给 x1 和 x2 高度相关的情况建立模型
X1 and X2 tend to be
highly correlated with each other for example.
来给 x1 和 x2 高度相关的情况建立模型
So specifically if you start
所以具体来说
to change the off diagonal
如果你改变协方差矩阵
entries of this covariance
非对角线上的元素
matrix you can get a different type of Gaussian distribution.
你会得到一种不同的高斯分布
And so as I
所以当我将非对角线的元素
increase the off-diagonal entries
from .5 to .8, what
从 0.5 增加到 0.8 时
I get is this distribution that
我会得到一个
is more and more thinly peaked
更加窄和高的
along this sort of x equals y line.
沿着 x=y 这条线的分布
And so here the
然后这个等高线图告诉我们
contour says that x and
x 和 y 看起来是一起增加的
y tend to grow together and
the things that are with
概率高的地方是这样的
large probability are if
either X1 is large and
要么 x1 很大 x2 也很大
Y2 is large or X1
is small and Y2 is small.
或者 x1 很小 x2 也很小
Or somewhere in between.
或者是这两者之间
And as this entry,
然后随着这个值
0.8 gets large, you get
0.8 增大
a Gaussian distribution, that's sort of
你会得到这样一个高斯分布
where all the probability lies on
差不多全部的概率都在一个很窄的范围内
this sort of narrow region,
where x is approximately equal to
也就是 x 几乎等于 y
y. This is a very
它是一个非常高
tall, thin distribution you know
而且非常薄的分布
line mostly along this line
几乎完全在 x 非常接近于 y 的这样一个
central region where x is
close to y. So this
非常窄的范围内
is if we set these
这是当我们把这些元素
entries to be positive entries.
设置为正数时的情况
In contrast if we set
相对地 如果我们
these to negative values, as
将它们设置为负数
I decreases it to -.5
随着我把它从 -0.5
down to -.8, then
减小到 -0.8
what we get is a model where
那么我得到的模型是
we put most of the probability
大部分的概率都在
in this sort of negative X
x1 和 x2 负相关的这样一个区域内
one in the next 2 correlation region,
and so, most of the
那么大部分的概率
probability now lies in this region,
几乎都落在 x1 和 -x2 差不多相等的区间内
where X 1 is about equal
to -X 2, rather than X
而不是 x1 等于 x2 的区间
1 equals X 2.
And so this captures a sort
所以这个捕捉到了
of negative correlation between x1
x1 和 x2 的负相关性
and x2.
And so this is
希望这些例子
a hopefully this gives you a sense of the
能让你体会到
different distributions that the
多元高斯分布所能展现的不同的分布
multivariate Gaussian distribution can capture.
So follow up in varying, the
到目前为止
covariance matrix sigma, the other
我一直在改变协方差矩阵 Σ
thing you can do is
你还可以做的事情是
also, vary the mean
改变平均值参数 μ
parameter mu, and so
operationally, we have mu
我们的 μ 本来是等于 0 0 的
equal 0 0, and so the
distribution was centered around
所以分布才会集中在
X 1 equals 0, X2 equals 0,
x1=0 x2=0 这个点周围
so the peak of the
所以这个分布的峰值在这里
distribution is here, whereas,
if we vary the values of
而如果我们改变 μ 的值
mu, then that varies the
它就会改变
peak of the distribution and so,
这个分布的峰值
if mu equals 0, 0.5,
所以如果 μ 等于 0 0.5
the peak is at, you know,
这个峰值就在
X1 equals zero, and X2
x1=0 x2=0.5 这里
equals 0.5, and so the
所以这个分布的
peak or the center of
峰值或者说中心
this distribution has shifted,
就会被移动
and if mu was 1.5
如果 μ 等于 1.5 -0.5
minus 0.5 then OK,
那么还是同样地
and similarly the peak
现在分布的峰值
of the distribution has now
就会被移动到另一个地方
shifted to a different location,
corresponding to where, you know,
这个新地方就对应
X1 is 1.5 and X2
x1=1.5 x2=-0.5 这个点
is -0.5, and so
所以改变参数 μ
varying the mu parameter, just shifts
就是在移动
around the center of this whole distribution.
这整个分布的中心
So, hopefully, looking at
所以 希望这些不同的图片
all these different pictures gives you
a sense of the sort
能够帮助你了解一下多元高斯分布
of probability distributions that
the Multivariate Gaussian Distribution allows you to capture.
所能描述的概率分布是什么样的
And the key advantage of it
它最重要的优势
is it allows you to
就是它可以让你
capture, when you'd expect
能够描述当两个特征变量之间
two different features to be
可能存在正相关
positively correlated, or maybe negatively correlated.
或者是负相关关系的情况
In the next video, we'll take
在接下来的视频中
this multivariate Gaussian distribution
我们要把这个多元高斯分布
and apply it to anomaly detection.
应用到异常检测中